The aortic valve is typically made up of three leaflets - the left, right, and posterior
leaflet and it opens during systole to allow blood to be ejected to the body.
During diastole, it closes, to allow the heart to fill with blood and get ready for another
systole.
If the aortic valve doesn’t open all the way, it gets harder to pump out to the body,
and this is called aortic stenosis.
If it doesn’t close all the way, then blood leaks back into the left ventricle, called
aortic valve regurgitation or aortic insufficiency.
Usually, the aortic valve opens to about 3-4 cm2, but with stenosis it can become less
than 1 cm2.
This is usually caused by mechanical stress over time, which damages endothelial cells
around the valves, causing fibrosis and calcification, which hardens the valve and makes it more
difficult to open completely.s This type usually shows up in late adulthood, with patients
over 60 years old.
Similarly, patient that have a bicuspid valve, with two leaflets, as opposed to a tricuspid
with three, are more at risk of fibrosis and calcification since the mechanical stress
that’s usually distributed between three leaflets is now being split by two leaflets,
and therefore they see more stress per leaflet.
Another important cause of aortic stenosis is chronic rheumatic fever, which can cause
repeated inflammation and repair, leading to fibrosis.
In this case, the leaflets can actually fuse together, called commissural fusion, which
can be an important distinction from the type caused by mechanical stress over time.
When the valve fuses together or hardens, it doesn’t open as easily, right?
And so as the left ventricle contracts, it creates this high pressure that eventually
pushes on the valve until it finally snaps open, causing a characteristic “ejection
click”.
Since the blood has to flow through a narrow opening, there’s turbulence which creates
noise or a murmur, which gets initially gets louder as more blood flows past the opening
and then quieter as the amount of blood flowing subsides because less remains in the ventricle.
This is called a crescendo-decrescendo murmur.
Since now it’s harder to open and push blood past this hardened valve, the left ventricle
has to generate higher pressures each time it contracts to get the same amount of blood
through.
To accomplish this, the left ventricle can thicken its muscles, called concentric left
ventricular hypertrophy.
This happens because new sarcomeres are added in parallel to the existing ones.
Even though you have this bulked up ventricle, the heart still might struggle to get enough
blood through the narrowed opening and the body, and ultimately to vital organs, and
that means that the person’s at risk of developing heart failure, and various symptoms
related to whatever organ’s involved.
For example, if there’s a reduction in blood flow to the brain, it could lead to syncope,
and a reduction in blood flow through coronary arteries to the heart’s own myocardium could
cause chest pain and angina.
Patients might not initially experience symptoms at rest, only during exercise, because exercise
requires more blood, right?
And the the heart isn’t able to increase blood flow through the small opening.
A final complication is called microangiopathic hemolytic anemia, which is essentially damage
to red blood cells as they’re forced through the smaller valve, splitting them into smaller
fragments called schistocytes, leading to hemoglobinuria, which is hemoglobin in the
urine.
Treatment is usually replacement of the valve, which often doesn’t happen until after the
onset of symptoms.
Alright so that was aortic stenosis, what about aortic regurgitation?
Well normally, right after the ventricle pumps blood out through the aortic valve, the valve
shuts and remains shut while the ventricle fills again.
With aortic regurgitation, or sometimes called aortic insufficiency, blood flows back from
the aorta into the left ventricle during diastole, or during ventricular filling.
About half of cases are caused by aortic root dilation.
Which is where the root dilates, or gets bigger, and in doing so pulls apart the leaflets,
making it harder for the valves to fit snugly together and close all the way and letting
some blood flow backward.
The vast majority, about 80% of aortic root dilations are idiopathic, which means that
the cause is unknown.
The remaining 20% of causes are things like aortic dissection, aneurysms, and syphilis,
all of which can widen the aortic root.
Besides root dilation, regurgitation may happen due to valvular damage, from something like
infective endocarditis, a bacterial infection of the inner lining of the heart, or again
from chronic rheumatic fever.
In this situation, the chronic inflammation leads to fibrosis, but instead of fusing the
valve leaflets together, it makes it so that they don’t form a nice seal and instead
let blood leak through.
Patients with aortic regurgitation will have an early decrescendo diastolic murmur, caused
by the blood flowing back through the valve.
Since blood’s leaking back from the aorta into the left ventricle, the left ventricular
blood volume increases which increases the stroke volume or the amount that the left
ventricle pumps out during contraction, or systole.
More blood pumped out of the heart per squeeze, requires more pressure, so systolic blood
pressure increases.
During diastole, though, there’s less blood volume in the aorta since some has leaked
back into the ventricle, which means that diastolic blood pressure decreases.
A higher systolic pressure and lower diastolic pressure means an increase in pulse pressure,
which is just systolic pressure minus diastolic pressure.
A large pulse pressure, meaning a large difference between systolic and diastolic pressure, is
referred to as a hyperdynamic circulation.
Patients with hyperdynamic circulation have bounding pulses, or water-hammer pulses because
the blood (which is mostly composed of water) slams like a hammer against the walls of the
arteries with each heartbeat.
These bounding pulses can be dramatic enough that they cause head bobbing that’s in tune
with the heartbeat, as well as causing the capillary beds in the fingernails to pulsate,
sometimes called Quincke’s sign.
Over time, the increase in blood volume in the left ventricle causes the chamber to grow
larger, called eccentric ventricular hypertrophy.
In this situation, new sarcomeres are added in series to existing ones.
Just like aortic stenosis, treatment for aortic regurgitation is replacement of the valve
after symptoms and left ventricular dysfunction develops.